<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A ievvell for the eare. By Ro. Wilkinson</title>
            <title>Sermon of hearing, or, jewell for the eare</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25652.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125576</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900651</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900651</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132794</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73426)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132794)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2088:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A ievvell for the eare. By Ro. Wilkinson</title>
                  <title>Sermon of hearing, or, jewell for the eare</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Robert, Dr. in Divinity.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for T. Pavier?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1602]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another edition of STC 25652.5, published in 1593 with title: A sermon of hearing, or, jewell for the eare.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Copy at reel 2088 has printing device and imprint cut out of title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132794:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132794:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p rend="roman">A IEVVELL FOR THE EARE.</p>
            <p rend="italic">By Ro. Wilkinſon</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi rend="roman">Rom. 10, 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <hi rend="italic">Faith commeth by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.</hi>
            </q>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="half page">
               <desc>〈 half page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:132794:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132794:2"/>
            <head rend="roman">To all thoſe that are desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, not onely to be hearers of <hi rend="italic">the worde, but dooers of the will of god.</hi> Grace, mercy and peace in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and Sauiour.</head>
            <p rend="italic">WIlling to ſatiſfie the eſpeciall entreaty of ſome, and for a generall benefite to all Gods Church, I haue ſet out to publike view, this Sermon of preparatiue, which I prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in my Pariſh Church at <hi>Horton</hi> in Kent. I know there is no word of God but hath his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, <note place="margin">2 Ti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 3, 16</note> for ſo ſaith paule, that al Scripture is profitable, but ſet this a part and we ſhall like him that after <note place="margin">Iohn 5, 5.</note> he had bin diſeaſed, eight and thirtie yeares, laye at the poole of Bethſaida for helpe, and yet was neuer the neare becauſe he had none to helpe him, nor knew not how to get in when the angell came downe to ſtirre the water: this is the reaſon why there are at this day ſo many vnfruitfull hearers, for that albeit mens ſoules are euen ſick for want of knowledge, though they haue lien at the well head
<pb facs="tcp:132794:3"/> and by the water of life, and had a continuall ſound of the Goſpell in their eare, yet in ſixe and fortie yeares this ignorance cannot be expelled, becauſe when the Angell of Gods will doth preach the word and ſtirre vp the water of life, they know not how to moue their eares toward it. This therfore (beloued) I haue ſet downe as a direction to teach men how to heare, that ſo often as the poole hereafter ſhal be ſtirred, and the word of God preached vnto you, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may know how to vſe it to your benefit, therefore learne this Sermon, and profit by all, neglect this and leeſe all. I haue called it a Iewell, as Chriſt called the Goſpell a pearle, for without this Iewel <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 4,</note> you ſhall neuer finde that pearle, I haue fitted it fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the eare: vnto which if ye apply it, it ſhal be an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament to the eare as <hi>Soloman</hi> ſaid of wiſedome <note place="margin">Prou. 1, 9.</note> it would be as a chaine to thy necke, therefore fail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not but apply it: hee which ſuffereth the Iewes to rob the Egiptians of their Iewels, and when they after melted them to make a calfe, did ſuffer vs to rob them of their ſpirituall Iewell, Let vs take hee leaſt for our abuſe of the word he ſtir vp the Iewe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againe to rob vs of this pearle of the Goſpell, and cauſe them to riſe againe by our fall, as we haue ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by theirs.</p>
            <p rend="italic">God of his mercy turne our harts, and teach vſ to imbrace his word as we ought. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi rend="roman">Yours in Chriſt. Ro. Wilkinſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:132794:3"/>
            <head rend="roman">A Iewell for the EARE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi rend="roman">Matthew 13, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q rend="italic">He that hath Eares to heare, let him heare.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>BEcauſe (beloued) the hearing of the worde is ſo holie a thinge, and holy thinges are not raſhlie to be attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: I haue thought good in this my entrance to lay downe a preparatiue, that we may knowe, with what reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence we are come into the temple, with what attention to heare, deſire to learne, and care to practiſe: for wel I remember, that when the Iſralites were ſommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to appeare before the Lorde in <hi rend="roman">Sina,</hi> they were firſt commaunded to ſanctifie <note place="margin">Exod. 19, 10, 11</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:132794:4"/> their harts, and waſhe their clothes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as <hi rend="roman">Moſes</hi> might not come néere the Angel til he had put of his ſhooes, becauſe <note place="margin">Exod. 3, 5</note> the grownd was holy wheron he ſtoode: this reaſon as néerely toucheth vs, for if the place be as holy, the exerciſe as holy now as then, why ſhould not we come as prepared as they, leaſt comming with vncircumciſed eares and vnprepared harts it be ſaid to vs as to him that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded him ſelfe at the wedding, <hi rend="roman">frinde, how cameſt thou hether not hauing on a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22, 12</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">wedding garment?</hi> In my firſt Sermon vpon thoſe words of the prophet. <hi rend="roman">For Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 62, 1</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">ſake I will not hold my toung,</hi> I let you know what was the duety of the ſpeaker, now it commeth in good order to tell you the duety of the hearer, for if it could any way concerne you to knowe our duety, much more auaileble will it be to learne your owne: for a declaration whereof I haue choſen this Text, <hi rend="roman">Hee that hath eares to heare let him heare.</hi> I know we are all by nature curious, and euery mans nature is to regarde an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans duty before his own, euen as
<pb facs="tcp:132794:4"/> 
               <hi rend="roman">Peter</hi> ſaid to Chriſt <hi rend="roman">Maiſt. what ſhal Iohn</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 21, 21</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">do?</hi> To whom Chriſt roundly anſwered again, <hi rend="roman">what is that to thee?</hi> as if he ment that euery man ſhould looke to himſelfe and let <hi rend="roman">Iohn</hi> alone: ſo would I perſwade you (for that ye are hearers) to learne the hearers duety, and let the ſpeaker a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: for albeit there be ſuch a reference betwéene hearing and ſpeaking, as they may not well be ſeuered, yet the neceſſity of hearing doth more generally concerne all, for God ſaid, <hi rend="roman">O earth, earth, earth, heare the worde of the Lord,</hi> but he neuer ſaide, <hi rend="roman">O earth, earth, earth,</hi> preach the worde of the Lord, for <hi rend="roman">Arons</hi> roabe befits <note place="margin">Ier. 22, 29</note> not euery man vpon the earth, but euery man is bounde to weare this Iewell at his eare, for <hi rend="roman">Faith commeth by hearing,</hi> as if Saint <hi rend="roman">Paule</hi> had ſaide, where is no hearing there can be no faith: therefore <note place="margin">Ro. 10, 17</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">Abraham</hi> ſpake out of heauen, and his voice did pearce euen the bowels of hel. <note place="margin">Luk. 16, 29</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">They haue Moſes and the Prophets let them heare them:</hi> and when he ſaieth, let them, it is more then a bare tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to ſay, they may if they will, for it
<pb facs="tcp:132794:5"/> is a flat charge, becauſe god therfore ſent <hi rend="roman">Moyſes</hi> &amp; the Prophets into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world of neceſſity ſhould hear. There is a kinde of people that thinke the whole burthen of the Saboth to lie vppon the ſpeaker, therefore Chriſte to wéede out that fancie ſaith likewiſe, <hi rend="roman">Take heed how</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 8, 18.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">you heare,</hi> to ſhow that there is a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and an arte of hearinge as well as of ſpeaking. Theſe two are fitly compared to a locke and a key, for as the key ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the lock and maketh entrance in at the doore, ſo the tongue of the miniſter ſhoulde open the eare of the hearer, that the ſpirit of knowledge and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding might paſſe into the heart: and ſo it ſhould ſeeme that ſpeaking is ordained to hearing, as the meanes is directed to the end: for when God had commanded that the ſkirts of <hi rend="roman">Arons</hi> robe ſhould be hunge about with Pomegranats of ſilke, and an intercourſe of bels betwéene them, the <note place="margin">Exod. 28, 34 &amp; 35.</note> reaſon was added, <hi rend="roman">That ſo oft as he mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the holye place, and went in and out before the Lord, his ſound ſhould be heard:</hi> but walles and windowes cannot
<pb facs="tcp:132794:5"/> heare, therefore by all likelihood that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was intended for men: and if for men why not for you? The holy Ghoaſt diſcended vppon the Apoſtles not in the ſhape of heads, that they ſhould onely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the word, nor of harts that they ſhuld onely loue the word, but like toongs that they ſhould preach the word: ſo that when God ſent out his diſciples with toongs, his meaning was that ye ſhoulde méete them in the halfe way with eares, and ſo ye ſée the correſpondence betwéene theſe two Scriptures, how iuſtly they fit and iumpe together, <hi rend="roman">for Syons ſake I wil not hold my tongue: Hee that hath eares to heare let him heare.</hi> For if it be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that we ſhould preach for <hi rend="roman">Syons</hi> ſake, then it is requiſite that <hi rend="roman">Syon</hi> ſhould heare for her owne ſake.</p>
            <p>This ſaying of our Sauiour, <hi rend="roman">He that hath eares &amp;c.</hi> is the argument by which he doth beg attention for the parable of the Sower, to ſhew that the doctrine it contained, was both ſo excellent in it ſelfe, and ſo neceſſarie for the world, as if a man were worth but his eares he could
<pb facs="tcp:132794:6"/> not chooſe but heare: and it may concern either all in generall, becauſe all haue ears, or the elect particulerly becauſe they onely haue eares to hear. For the farmer, if there were no other reaſon why men ſhould heare but this, becauſe God hath giuen an eare, yet it bindeth very ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: therefore ſée how God ſpeaketh vnto vs euen in the fleſhly inſtrument of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: Chriſt doth not vrge vppon vs the dignity of himſelfe the ſpeaker, neither the neceſſity of the doctrine, nor the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which befalleth to a man by not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: but leauing al theſe arguments, he reaſoneth againſt vs euen from fleſh and bloud, and proueth euen by the member and inſtrument of the eare, that men ought to be hearers of the worde. Wee muſt not think our eares are giuen vs for worldly vſes onely, to harken after our profit, to liſten to him that can teach vs a Goſpell of gold, that can tickle our eares with muſicke, or our mindes with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt <note place="margin">Apoc. 2, 3.</note> mirth, but God hath planted the eare for ſpiritual vſes, euen as <hi rend="roman">Saint Iohn ſaith, let him that hath an eare heare what</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:132794:6"/> 
               <hi rend="roman">the ſpirit ſaith:</hi> mark well the words, for that we ſhould marke them he hath ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times repeated them. <hi rend="roman">Let him that hath an eare heare,</hi> not what the worlde ſaith, nor what the fleſh ſaith, nor what the diuell ſaith, but what the ſpirit ſaith: that if both ſpeak at once we ſhould liſten to the ſpirit, &amp; turne the deafe ſide to the diuell: and if the eare be the doore of the hart, then fitly might <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> ſay, <hi rend="roman">Lift vp</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24, 7.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">your heads ye gates and be ye open you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting doores:</hi> and not euery gueſt, <hi rend="roman">but the king of glorie ſhall come in.</hi> And what maruell is it if the eares were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to holy vſes, ſince there is no part or member of the body or ſoul which god hath not ordained to ſome ſpirituall end. Did god create the eie that it ſhould only be a light to the bodie, and in no ſort giue light to the ſoul? or did he not rather principally create it, that it might tel the ſoule what beauty was in the viſible cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that the ſoule might thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture what glory is in the inuiſible god. Did god giue man a mouth onely to bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and buy withall, or call for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities
<pb facs="tcp:132794:7"/> of this life, or rather to ſinge of his teſtimonies and ſet foorth his praiſe? O god my hart is prepared (ſaith <hi rend="roman">Dauid)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 108.</note> and ſo is my toung: and then he preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inferreth vpon it, I will ſing and giue praiſe, for what ſhould he do with a tong that giueth not praiſe. God hath giuen vs witte and braines, but not onely for worldly vſes and deuiſes, not to inuent inſtruments of muſick as <hi rend="roman">Iuball</hi> did, nor workes of braſſe as <hi rend="roman">Tubal-kain</hi> did, nor vnderſtandinge policies as <hi rend="roman">Achitophel</hi> did, but to ſtudy for heauenly wiſedome <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.</note> as <hi rend="roman">Soloman</hi> did, to meditate of Gods lawes as <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> did. God hath giuen vs harts and affections, and yet not to loue the world, but to ſet our affections who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one him: in a word, there is no part or member in ſoule and body which ought not as a <hi rend="roman">Nazarite</hi> to bee conſecrate and vowed to the ſeruice of God. <hi rend="roman">Saloman</hi> iudged thoſe dayes to be euill dayes, wherein a man coulde not vſe his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to remember the Creator, wherein the kéepers ſhould tremble, the ſtronge men ſhoulde bow, they that looke out at
<pb facs="tcp:132794:7"/> the windowes ſhould waxe darke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the doores ſhoulde bee ſhut by the baſe ſound of the grinding, and the daughters of ſinging ſhould be abaſed, thoſe hee iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged euill daies, as if it were as good in a manner to haue noe handes as ſuch trembling handes: to haue no ioints as, ſuch féeble ioints: to haue no eies as blind eies: to be without an eare, as to haue a deafe eare: then by the contrary, if theſe be euil dayes, wherein a man cannot vſe his members, they muſt néedes be good wherein God hath giuen a frée vſe of all. So as it may ſéeme that God in ech part or member of a mans body, did intende ſome ſpeciall vſe for his worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, vnto which if the partes in youth were not imployed in the euil daies, they would be fruitleſſe and vnprofitable: Will thoſe eies which are wont to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and gaze after euery vanity, wil they in the euill dayes bee learned and taught to behold gods wil in his precious word, and his great glory in all the creatures? Will the toong which hath euer bin accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed &amp; invred with all vices, as lying,
<pb facs="tcp:132794:8"/> ſtandering, ſcurrility and blaſphemy, wil it in the euel daies be taught to ſound out the praiſe of god. Will thoſe eares which haue béene ſo accuſtomed with filthe and folly, will they in the euil daies be taught to heare the word of God: therfore while we haue eies, let vs beholde, and <hi rend="roman">he that hath eares let him heare.</hi> It is not only a bare gift of nature or worke of the womb that wee haue eies, eares, and tongues, <note place="margin">Act. 17, 28</note> but it is euen the <hi rend="roman">grace of God fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue,</hi> for in him we liue, we mooue, and haue our being: and god beſtoweth not his gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces for nothing: I ſay there is no mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a mannes body but carrieth in it a print of Gods loue and teſtimony of his grace: but aboue all the reſt more ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, are we beholding to him for our eies and eares, for that by theſe twoe as by a channel the knowledge of God is conuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into our ſoules, for by the eie we come to the naturall mans diuinity in ſuruay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the creatures, becauſe as <hi rend="roman">Paul</hi> ſayeth <note place="margin">Rom. 1, 20</note> the viſible things of god <hi rend="roman">that is his eternall power and Godhead are ſeene by the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the worlde,</hi> if they were ſeene by
<pb facs="tcp:132794:8"/> the creation, then our eie is our ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter to bring vs to the knowledge of the Creator: but that knowledge is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect as the glimmering of a light, but by our eare more ſpecially and expreſſely we attaine to the knowledge of Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed will: ſo that God neuer commeth ſo néere a mans ſoule as when he entreth in by the doore of the eare, therefore, the eare is a moſt precious member if men knew how to vſe it: and better were it to looſe a better member the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to want it, if a man looſe an eie an arme or a legge, he iudgeth himſelfe as a cripple, vnworthy to liue amonge men, and fit for no place but for a ſpittle: and yet theſe are but maimes in the body: but if God take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the vſe of hearing, it is a ſigne he is angry indeede, and threatneth a famine to the ſoule, for the ſoule feedeth at the eare, as the body by the mouth: therefore better looſe all then looſe it. Our Sauiour <note place="margin">Math. 5. 29 30.</note> Chriſt ſaid, If thy right eie cauſe thee to offende plucke it out, if thy right hande cauſe thee to offende cut it off, but he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſaide, if thine eare offend thée ſtop it
<pb facs="tcp:132794:9"/> vp, for there is a greater vſe of it then of hands or eies: for a man may want his handes and haue faithe, or his eies and haue faith, but hardlye can hee want his eares and haue faith: for <hi rend="roman">Faith commeth by hearing,</hi> not by ſéeing, or féeling, but it entreth in at the eare, and ſo ſinketh downe to the hart: therfore <hi rend="roman">He that hath an eare let him heare what the ſpirit ſaith,</hi> and conſider that God gaue the eare, that men ſhould profit by hearing, euen as he beſtowed his tallentes that the factors ſhould gaine and profit by them. We are Gods factors, and our members are his tallents, the eie is a tallent, the tongue is a tallent, and the eare is a tallent: for this benefitte a Chriſtian hath, that the righteous Mammon is portable, thogh the vnrighteous be not, for where as the men of the world haue no wealth but in their cheſtes and barnes, the righteous carrie theirs about them in their ſoules and bodies, for euerye member is a tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, which béeing faithfully and wiſely imployed, there is a treaſure laide vp for the ſoule in heauen, but béeing not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied,
<pb facs="tcp:132794:9"/> there is a day of reckoning when euery man accordinge to the tallent of grace beſtowed on him ſhall be bound to yéelde an accompt of his ſtewardſhipp, euen of our eyes, our toongs and eares, wherof we make ſo ſlender a reckoning. At that time it will finally availe vs to ſaie, I emploied mine eares to earthly vſes, for then it wilbe ſaid to vs as to him that buried his tallent in the earth, <hi rend="roman">Go take him, binde him hand and foote:</hi> then ſhall thoſe hands be chained with fetters, which by example of their refuſed to glorifie god: then ſhall thoſe eyes be afrighted with horrible and gaſtly viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which in the creatures would neuer behould the glory of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then ſhall that toonge be tormemted with vnquenchable flames which neuer ſought to ſet forth the praiſe of God, and then ſhall thoſe eares be filled with yelling, with how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and gnaſhing of téeth, which neuer regarded to heare the worde of God: therefore whoſoeuer he be to whom God hath giuen an eare let him heare.</p>
            <p>But what is that which Chriſt ſayth?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:132794:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">He that hath an eare to heare:</hi> as if there were an eare which were not to heare; we are to vnderſtand it as a note of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall difference, for though we haue all eares, yet all haue not eares to heare: but as there is a kinde of idle or Idoll Paſtors which haue mouthes and ſpeake not, ſo there is a kinde of idle hearers which haue eares and heare not, which ſit in their ſeates as images in the glaſſe windowes, bending their knees, lifting vp their hands, and caſting vp their eies, yet after ſo many yeares, and ſo many maſſes had neuer the honeſty to giue one Amen: only this difference there is, that whereas the Saintes in the glaſſe win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes kéepe out the winde, theſe fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hearers poſſeſſe the places wherein they do no good at all: and let it not ſéeme ſtrange, that there ſhould be eares which are not to heare, for <hi rend="roman">Paul</hi> ſayeth of the Iewes that <hi rend="roman">God had giuen them a ſpirit</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11, 2</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">of ſlumbring, eies that they ſhould not ſee, and eares that they ſhoulde not heare,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had the inſtrument but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the right vſe, for onely thoſe may be
<pb facs="tcp:132794:10"/> ſaid to haue eares to heare which firſt by our ſelues are vowed, and then after by the ſpirit of God are ſanctified to that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe: ſo that Chriſt ſpeaketh eſpecially of the children of the Church, for they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue ſanctified and prepared eares. This therfore (beloued) is that we deſire to learne how to prepare and prouide our ſelues, that we may bring eares to heare and heare with profitte, leaſt we departe from the Church, as the fiue fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins from the gates of heauen, as good not come as come for no good: therefore the firſt thing I am to exhort you to is, that we may come together for though priuate prayer be not vnprofitable, and familiar exhortation want not his vſe, yet our méeting together hath a ſpeciall bleſſing promiſed to it by him which ſaid, <hi rend="roman">where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the middeſt of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18, 20</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">them:</hi> and indéed our hearing preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth comming, for we cannot heare toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther except we come together, therefore <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> ſet comming firſt, and hearing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <note place="margin">Pſal. 34, 11</note> and ſaid, <hi rend="roman">Come Children and harken,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:132794:11"/> 
               <hi rend="roman">and I will teach ye the feare of the Lord:</hi> ſo ſay I to you, firſt come and then hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, let it bee with you as with <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> who reioyced when they ſaid, <hi rend="roman">Come let vs goe into the houſe of the Lord, becauſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 122, 1</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">one day in Gods courtes is better then a thouſand elſe where</hi> and who had not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be a doore-kéeper in the houſe of god, then to dwel in the tabernacle of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</p>
            <p>Conſider what ſpirite was in <hi rend="roman">Dauid,</hi> when he ſaide, that the Sparrow and Swallow were bleſt, becauſe they might lodge their yong ſo néere the alter, as if a poore bird were to be enuied for hir neſt: or rather to teach men that they ought to preaſe as hard to touch but the walles of the temple, as ſhe that deſired to touch but the hem of Chriſts garment: and that if any on ſhould ſaie, <hi rend="roman">Come let vs go into the houſe of the Lord,</hi> men ought to be as the curtens of the Tabecnacle, whereof but one being drawen, all the reſt did followe after; the Centurion boaſted that he had ſuch ſeruants as if he <note place="margin">Mat. 8, 9</note> ſaid to one, come, he comes, and yet he
<pb facs="tcp:132794:11"/> called them for his owne priuate profit, but God a greater maiſter then the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion ſaith come yea and calleth vs for our profit, and yet we come not: nay e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery creeping worme will put vs to ſhame and condemne vs, for God ſpake <note place="margin">Pſ. 105, 34</note> but the worde and the Graſh-hoppers came, yea and Catterpillers innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but God hath ſpoken to vs many words, and yet our number (God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) is numerable enough: (there is a kind of Catterpiller that commeth to the Church, a ſacrilegious vermin deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring holy thinges, which liue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweete that they ſweate not for, but they come vnſent for for God neuer ſpake to them, neither do I commend their dilligence in comming, for a bleſſed thinge it were if God ſhould ſend a weſte winde to blow them into the ſea:) but I ſpeake of thoſe poore creatures whom God neuer calleth but they come and are obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and their obedience aſcendeth vp to heauen, and from heauen is deſcended back againe to condemne our diſobedience, for from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen God ſpake it, that the Oxe ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:132794:12"/> come to his owner and the Aſſe to his <note place="margin">Eſay. 1, 3.</note> maiſters cribb, but Iſraell Gods owne people would not vnderſtand, nor come: O therfore all ye that are Gods people come and hearken; and take this leſſon withall, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye yeeld not to come as <hi rend="roman">Peter</hi> yeelded to forgiue his brother, ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times and then ha done; for I ſay vnto you not ſeuen times but ſeuentie times ſeuen times, yea ſo often as the ſeuenth day ſhall come vpon you come and hollow it. The <hi rend="roman">At<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enians</hi> came to heare <hi rend="roman">Paule</hi> but it was for nouilty of his doctrin, as there be (I am in doubt and I feare it) in this place who are come to heare the Sermon onely becauſe it is new and ſtraunge to haue a preacher, but when preachinge ſhall waxe ſtale, they will not heare the voice of the charmer charme hee neuer ſo wiſely: theſe men for a brunt are verye deuout, as he who receiued the worde in ſtony grownd, reioycing at the firſt, and hearing it with ioy, but that ioy indured <note place="margin">Mat. 13, 20</note> but a while, for his zeale poſſeſſed him like an ague, very hotte for the time but when the fit was ouer, he fell to his olde
<pb facs="tcp:132794:12"/> bias, as the dog to his vomit: remember <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> ſaith. <hi rend="roman">Bleſſed are they that dwell in <note place="margin">Pſal. 84, 4</note> Gods houſe.</hi> The Church of God is not like a Inne, for once or twice to ſoiourne in, but it is to dwell in, and dwellinge is a continuall abiding, wee muſt haue our harts there, our treaſure there, and bring our Children there, as the Swallowes laies her young by the alter: in a worde we muſt altogether dwell there, that at what time ſoeuer Chriſt ſhall come he may finde vs in the temple and not in a Tauerne, in the houſe of prayer, and not in a den of théeues. We neede not ſay (beloued) as <hi rend="roman">Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi rend="roman">Let vs make vs three tabernacles,</hi> for God hath built vs a temple and tabernacle to our hands, onely let vs bringe readdy affections and ſay, <hi rend="italic">Bonum ect eſſe hic,</hi> 
               <hi rend="roman">it is good for vs to be heere:</hi> which if with aſſiduitie and dil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence ye ſhall performe, then will I ſay of you as <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> of himſelfe, <hi rend="roman">The zeale of gods houſe hath eaten you vp</hi> but if ye <note place="margin">Pſal. 69, 9</note> faint and waxe colde, I muſt ſay that you haue eaten vp your zeale, therefore in the name of god let vs come with dilligence,
<pb facs="tcp:132794:13"/> Gods liberality calleth for dilligence at your hands, who of all the trées in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice did aſke for himſelfe but one, of all the daies in ſeauen aſketh ye but one, if ye will giue him another hee will accept it as a fréewill offringe, but but fayle not to giue him one, and pay it faithfully, who of his owne doth aſke yet one ſo ſparingly. I knowe what will be your excuſes, ye haue marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a wife, or bought a yoake of oxen, therefore ye cannot come, but deceiue not your ſelues, for theſe are no excuſes? ſhall a wife kéepe you backe from follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing Chriſte: yet better it were for a man to liue alone then to haue ſuch an helper: what though <hi rend="roman">Adam</hi> ſaid, <hi rend="roman">Man <note place="margin">Gen. 2, 24</note> ſhall forſake father and mother to cleaue <note place="margin">Luk. 14, 26</note> to his wife, yet Chriſt ſaide, a man muſt hate father and mother and wife to come to him.</hi> But ye will pleade that ye haue bought a yoke of oxen? <hi rend="italic">Poſtponetur Deus bonibus qui nos aequauit Angelis</hi> ſaith an old writer? Will you ſet God behinde your Oxen who hath made you equall with Angels? Theſe thinges are good:
<pb facs="tcp:132794:13"/> but in their order and due place, but ſéeke ye firſt the kingdome of God and the righteouſneſſe therof, and then let wiues and Oxen follow after: for euen our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary buſineſſes and lawfull affaires if they hinder vs from Gods ſeruice, are turned into ſinne, euen as the pure wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi rend="roman">Egipt</hi> were turned into bloud. If lawfull buſineſſes may not hinder our comming to the Church of God, then much leſſe may idle ſportes and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full games detaine vs: if bargaininge and wiuing may not excuſe vs, much leſſe will piping and dauncing. The Saboth is a day of holy reſt, not of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy ryot: the Iraelites might not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their Manna vpon it, and may we <note place="margin">Exo. 16, 26</note> runne a rioting vpon it? What would they doe to them whom they finde prophaninge Godes Saboth with drunken delightes, who ſtoned him to <note place="margin">Nú. 15, 26</note> death whome they founde gatheringe ſtickes for needefull vſe? But this is our corruption of nature, euerye idle ſporte prouokes vs to ſacriledge, to rob God of his glory in his ſaboth, and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb facs="tcp:132794:14"/> it to the Diuell: <hi rend="italic">Diabolus te vocat et ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Mundus te vocat et venis, Caro te vocat et venis, Cultus Dei te vocat et non venis,</hi> ſaith an antient father. The deuel calleth by tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and ye yeelde vnto it, the worlde calleth and ye liſten to it, the fleſh calleth and ye come to it, but the worſhip of God calleth and ye care not for it. <hi rend="roman">Diogenes</hi> to try the nature of the <hi rend="italic">Athenians,</hi> diſguiſed himſelfe vnhandſomely, daunced rudely, and ſet his voice to ſinge ilfauordly, and the people came flocking about him: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold (ſaith he) the nature of this people, ſo oft as I tooke vpon me to ſpeake of an honeſt life or vertuous conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they paſſed by me as a viſited perſon, and left me alone, but now I frame my ſelfe to make ſports like a foole, they like a flocke of fooles come preaſing about mee: there is nothing that chokes mens zeale ſo much as that they hunte ſo gréedily after vanity of the worlde, neither was there any reaſon why <hi rend="roman">Eſau</hi> was prophane but becauſe hee was a man of the fielde, for while he was hunting for veniſon abrod, <hi rend="roman">Iacob</hi> catcht vp the bleſſing and birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb facs="tcp:132794:14"/> at home, euen as often times it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out that while Gods bleſſinge is a dealing in the Church, the people are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling and rioting in the ſtréete, therfore come to the Church and God will bleſſe you.</p>
            <p>When you haue obtained of your ſelus to come, the next thing it is to performe attention, for <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> ſaith not, come chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and heare, but come and hearken: and if hearing were inough to ſatiſfie a Saboth day, then might ye driue in your oxen too for they can apprehend an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſounde as well as ye, but though they haue eares, yet they haue not eares to heare. In the Scripture hearing and harkning is all one, and our harkning it is <hi rend="italic">Opus animi non Auris,</hi> as one ſaithe, a work of the mind and not of the outward eare, a dilligent obſeruing in the mind of that which is ſaid, therefore the <hi rend="italic">Gramari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> do fitly ſignifie attention vnder the word. <hi rend="italic">Animaduertere, vt animum aduertere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus non aurem</hi> that wee ſhoulde not onely turne our ears but ſet our mind to it: but that can a beaſt neuer do becauſe he hath
<pb facs="tcp:132794:15"/> no mind, and he that bringeth his eares to Church and leaueth his mind at home he commeth like a beaſt.</p>
            <p>Our attention haue fiue great enemies, <note place="margin">The ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</note> the firſt is a ſtraying thought, when all the powers of our ſoule ſhould wait vpon the voice of the preacher, then are our minds in our coffers, or in our paſtures, or where they ſhould not be: wherefore pray for a ſteddy and ſtayed harte. The ſecond is a wandring eie, gazing after e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery picture, vpon euery mote, or flie, and rolling vp and down in euery corner, for as <hi rend="roman">Soloman ſaith the eies of a foole are in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17, 24 Eccl. 2, 14.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">euery corner. But a wiſe mans eies are in his head</hi> The thirde is a néedeleſſe ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſtirring of the bodie, a fum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling with handes, a ſhuffling with the féete, a riſinge and remouinge from place when there is noe cauſe to prouoke vs: and let it not ſéeme ſtrange that theſe ſmall trifles ſhoulde hinder our attention, for euen the little birds of the aire did picke vppe the ſéede of the word, leaſt it ſhoulde take roote and goe down to the hart. The fourth is an vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent
<pb facs="tcp:132794:15"/> talking and vnciuill laughing in the Churche, as if the Temple of God were a place of mart or exchange, where euery man might ſingle out his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fréely diſcourſe <hi rend="italic">de omni e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te &amp; non en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> of euery matter &amp; occaſion offred &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, theſe are they that make the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God a den of theeues. The fift is a ſeruice &amp; ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celes ſléeping, for ſome ther be who are no ſooner in their ſeats but their harts are a ſleepe, as if they came to ſee vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, &amp; looketh with Iacob to ſée the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels going vp, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they might as wel ſee <hi rend="italic">Eutichus</hi> fallinge downe: Therefore quicken your ſences, rouze vp your dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and remember him which ſaid to his diſciples, <hi rend="roman">Could yea not watch with mee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26, 40</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">one houre?</hi> To theſe fiue ye may adde (if ye pleſe) a ſixt which of al the reſt is moſt ſcandolous and offenſiue, and that is a ſhamful departing out of the church and violent breaking from the congregation, wherin a man doeth as it were openly proteſt, that he is exceeding weary, &amp; hath but too much for his mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ey, ſo that <hi rend="roman">Ioſeph</hi> was neuer more willing to depart out
<pb facs="tcp:132794:16"/> of priſon, then he out of the Church, nor <hi rend="roman">Simeon</hi> better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to die when he ſaid. <hi rend="roman">Lord now letteſt thou thy ſeruant departe in peace.</hi> But ſuch men can hardly depart in peace, for ſeldom it is when they leaue not behinde them, both the grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>After attention is required remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, to lay it vpp in the ſtore-houſe of our memory, for what auaileth it to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue for the time and ſo ſoon as we be gone to forget all, to ſuffer the birdes to pick vp the ſéede which Chriſt had ſowen before. <hi rend="roman">Saint Iames</hi> compareth ſuch a manne to one beholdinge his face in a glaſſe, who goeth his waye and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth imediately what manner of man he was: and fitlie are ſuch eares reſembled to a ſieue, which while ye dip it in the <note place="margin">Iam. 1, 23 24.</note> water receiueth it in at a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d holes, but take it vp, and the water runneth out faſter then euer it came in: ſo is it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> forgetfull hearers, they marke atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, conceiue preſently, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or a time are touched inwardly, but the next toy
<pb facs="tcp:132794:16"/> driueth all out againe, but <hi rend="roman">Bleſſed are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 11, 28</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">they that heare the worde of God and keepe it:</hi> it ſhould ſéeme that <hi rend="roman">Peter</hi> carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch a ſieue in his head, elſe how could the diuell ſifte him as wheat. for noe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner had Chriſt forewarned him that he would forſweare him, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dieull ſifted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde out of his eares, and he forgat it, and ſo not remembring the wordes was the cauſe of <hi rend="roman">Peters</hi> apoſtaſie, for ſo ſoone as he remembered the wordes, the texte ſaith he went out and wept bitterly: ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore let vs not onely heare but remember too, for that ſpirit which ſaith <hi rend="roman">O my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78, 1 Prou. 3, 1</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">heare my law,</hi> ſaith likewiſe <hi rend="roman">my Sonne forget not my law.</hi> Therefore God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed helps of memorie to the Iſralites, commanding them to binde his wordes vppon their handes for a ſigne, that they ſhould be as frontlets between their eies, that they ſhoulde write them vppon the poſts of their houſes, and on their gates, and in a worde that they ſhoulde vſe all helps againſt forgetfulnes, for that was Gods meaning and no more: and if we ſeeke for a helpe indeede, then conference
<pb facs="tcp:132794:17"/> is the helpe, when a man is delighted to talk of that at home which hath béen ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at the Church, for it may be that wil pearce into the head at a ſecond repeting, which at the firſt report would not, euen as a naile may be driuen in at a ſecond or third ſtroke, which could not at the firſt: and indéede it is Gods commanndement to the Iſralites, that they ſhould talke of his law among their children when they were in their houſes, when they taulked or elſe walked by the waye, as alſo at their vpriſing and downe laying: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs thinke that this charg concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs likewiſe, and ſaye with <hi rend="roman">Dauid. Our tongue ſhall talke of thy righteouſnes <note place="margin">Pſa. 72, 24</note> all the day long</hi> that at what time ſoeuer Chriſt ſhal come he may finde vs talking of his teſtimonies, as when he ouertooke his deſciples walking to <hi rend="italic">Emaus,</hi> he found them communing of his death and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. After attention and memory the laſt and chiefe point is to lay it to the harte, for God eſpecially reſpecteth the hart, and if that bee wanting hee miſſeth it at the <note place="margin">Eſa. 29, 13</note> firſt, and ſaith, <hi rend="roman">This people honoureth</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:132794:17"/> 
               <hi rend="roman">me with their lips, or with their eares, but their hart is far from me.</hi> It is a ſmal thing to remember onely what was ſaide, it is but a ſigne of a good memory at the beſt, and if that be ſufficient then let the diuel come into the temple too, for he hath me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morye more then inough, to quote any Scripture againſt Chriſt, or whoſoeuer ſhall encounter him, and many hipocrits which hang vpon the Church haue a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſwimming in their braine, a ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue diuinity, by which they can holde talke at a table to diſcourſe of any pointe <note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> in Religion, or courſe out a controuerſie to the proofe, but God is not ſerued with wit and memory, therefore he ſaith fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi rend="roman">Thou ſhalt lay vp theſe words in thy hart, and in thy ſoule</hi> To lay Gods word to the hart is to take hold of it by the hart and apply it to the conſcience, as when we hear of gods mercy to be rauiſht with ioye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and when wee heare of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be ſtricken with fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when we heare of his promiſes to riſe vp in hope, when we heare of our ſins to repent and loath our ſelues. This is the laying of
<pb facs="tcp:132794:18"/> the word to our hart, and thus did <hi rend="roman">Marie</hi> when ſhe heard what ſtraung things the ſhepheards reported from the Angels: <hi rend="roman">Saint Luke</hi> ſaith, <hi rend="roman">She kept all thoſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and pondred them in her hart,</hi> A ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial <note place="margin">Luk. 2, 10</note> help to this is an often reuoluing and meditating in our minds of that we haue hearde, for <hi rend="roman">Dauid</hi> did not onely talke of Gods teſtimonies amongſt his friends, but being alone likewiſe did meditate of his law, for ſo he ſaith, that in Gods law was his continuall meditation and that both euening and morning, and ſeauen times in a day, and it hath bin the practiſe of Gods ſaints from time to time, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into continual meditation of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and of his iudgments. It is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in <hi rend="italic">Iſaac</hi> that euery euening hee went <note place="margin">Ge. 24, 63 Eſay 5, 12, 14.</note> out to meditate: in the law thoſe beaſtes were onely cleane which chewed the cud, by which was figured a ſpirituall medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating &amp; ruminating of heauenly things: and it is the cauſe of much vncleaneſſe in mens liues, and of much iudgement vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the world, becauſe they meditate not of Gods waies. Indeed ſaith the prophet,
<pb facs="tcp:132794:18"/> 
               <hi rend="roman">The harpe and violl, the Timbrell &amp; pipe, and wine are in their bankets, but the works of God they conſider not, therefore hell hath enlarged it ſelfe and opened her mouth, and they that reioyced ſhall goe downe into it: and ſo ſaithe the Prophet Ieremie. That the whole land is fallen into deſolation becauſe there is none that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth in his hart <note place="margin">Ier. 12, 11</note>
               </hi> Therfore in the name of God (beloued) let vs prepare our eares and harts, that we may firſt heare, then remember, and laſt of all lay vp the word in our harts, for this is the right hearing, and he that heareth hath not onely eares, but eares to heare, I would ye did conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that euery man by his obedience in this regard is iudged of what flock he is, for ſo ſaith Chriſt, <hi rend="roman">My ſheepe heare my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10, 27</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">voice:</hi> ſo that if a man be deſirous to hear, then ſtraight he is iudged to be of chriſts flocke: but if the word be vnſauory, and bréed no delight in his hart: it is a ſhreud preſumption that that man is a Goate: And great reaſon we haue to delight in Gods voice, for there is no word procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of his mouth, but it ſauoureth
<pb facs="tcp:132794:19"/> of mercy and ſaluation to the ſoule, for ſo <note place="margin">Cant. 5, 13</note> the Church teſtified of Chriſte, that his lips are like to Lillies dropping downe pure mirrhe, and how then ſhould God indure our contempt who prefer the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell before him: nay God will endite vs not onely of contempt but of mockery too, for if we ſhall beſéech God to ſupply the meanes of hearing, and ſend down a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet amongſt vs, and when that Prd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet commeth, ſhall ſhut our ears againſt him, what is that but a mocke? Beſides what an vnreſonable thing is it that we deſire God to heare vs, who could neuer vouchſafe to heare him, if we ſtand in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny néede of God how clamorous are wee and importunate vpon him.</p>
            <p>Heare my prayer O Lord, bow down thine ear vnto my ſupplicatton, and why hideſt thou thy face and forgetteſt all our afflictions, and if God ſéeme a little to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay vs, how haſty are we vpon him, come Lord Ieſus, come quickly and make noe long tarrying my God, and O god make haſt to help vs: but when God ſpeaks to vs there is none that turneth his eare,
<pb facs="tcp:132794:19"/> as if we had him in a ſtring, that he were bound to vs and not we to him: therfore it ſhall come to paſſe that we ſhall pray and he ſhall not heare vs, for ſo he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. <hi rend="roman">Becauſe I haue called and ye refuſed,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prou. 7, 24 26, 27, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">I will alſo laugh at your deſtruction, and mocke when your feare commeth, when your feare commeth like a ſodain deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and your deſtruction like a whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winde, when affliction and anguiſh ſhall come vpon you, then ſhall they call vpon me but I will not anſwere, they ſhall ſeeke me earelie but they ſhall not finde me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they hated knowledge.</hi> God ſhall take from you either the preaching of the worde as he threatneth by <hi rend="roman">Amos. I will</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amo. 8, 11</note> 
               <hi rend="roman">ſend a famine into the lande, not a famine of bread, nor thirſt for water, but of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the word of the Lord.</hi> Or God ſhall take from you the Preacher of the word, when ye ſhall runne from coaſt to coaſte, and ſhall finde none to preach peace vnto your conſciences, or at the leaſt god ſhall take away the guifts of the Preacher be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the hardnes of your harts. It is a notable obſeruation of Saint <hi rend="roman">Gregorie</hi> that God doeth ſometime multiply his
<pb facs="tcp:132794:20"/> gifts and his ſpirit vppon the Preacher becauſe the hearer is deſirous to learne: and ſometime againe he doth take away his giftes and his ſpirite from the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher euen for a plague and iudgement v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the people, becauſe they neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to heare or care to learne. Therefore doe ye prepare your heartes and eares to heare and I doubt not but god will mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply his ſpirit and ſend a bleſſing vppon theſe my labours. And of this let me ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe you before hand, that no one of you at any time preſume to ſet his foote with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe wals, who firſt ſetteth not down with himſelfe to practiſe in his life what here hee heareth with his eare. Some come not to haue their liues reſormed, but to haue their eares tickled as at a play: ſome come for nouelty, ſome for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, ſome to ſléepe, ſome to ſée, and ſome to be ſeen, but few to practiſe: but let theſe things be farre from you, for our ſauiour Chriſt ſayth. <hi rend="roman">He that is of God, beareth gods words:</hi> (nay he goeth further in the <note place="margin">Iohn. 8, 47</note> ſame place ſpeaking to the vnbeleeuing Iewes, <hi rend="roman">ye therefore heare them not, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:132794:20"/> ye are not of God,</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Saint Iames</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1, 22</note> ſaith, that he deceiueth himſelfe who is onely a hearer of the word and not a doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: for Gods word is a leuen, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is to turne the whole lumpe into his owne nature, to ſeaſon and make it like it ſelfe as when you haue heard a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of humility to ſhew forth the fruite of that Sermon in your liues and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaſions: when you haue heard a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of repentance to be ſtricken in hart with a feeling of your ſinnes: when you haue heard of Gods iudgementes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt blaſphemy, couetouſneſſe, lying, ſtealing, againſt vſury or prophaning of the Sabboths, euery man to ſet downs with himſelfe I will ſurely (with Gods help) purge my ſelfe of this and that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and amend in my ſelfe what I now ſee is amiſſe, then may we ſay of you ye are our Sermon as <hi rend="roman">Paule ſaide to the Corrinthians ye are our Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtle <note place="margin">2 cor. 3, 2,</note>
               </hi> When whatſoeuer doctrine hath flowed out of our mouths doth ſpring vp as freſhly in your liues: let vs therefore ſay with Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, <hi rend="roman">O Lord prepare the harts of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:132794:21"/> vnto thee,</hi> ſend downe thy holy ſpirit into our hartes and into our eares, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern vs when we come to hear, for <hi rend="roman">paule</hi> may plant, and <hi rend="roman">Apollo</hi> water, but thou muſt giue increaſe, and in vaine ſhal the voice of the preacher beate vpon the doore of our eares, vnleſſe thou fill our hartes with thy ſpirit, which we beſéech thée of thy infinite mercy and goodneſſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that we may proceed from grace to grace, vntil we come to the ſtate of glory vnto which the Lord of his mercy bringe uſ. To the ſonne and to the holy ghoaſt, (thrée perſons but one God) bee aſcribed all praiſe dominion and glory nowe and for euermore. <hi rend="italic">Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer rend="roman">Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:132794:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
